University of Connecticut
© 2009 University of Connecticut
University of Connecticut, Cooperative Extension Service Records.
undated, 1888-
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
University of Connecticut, Cooperative Extension Service.; University of Connecticut, Cooperative Extension System.
50.7 linear feet.
MSS19700003
The collection contains publications, reports, studies, documents and ephemeral materials collected and used as background and research for the development and preparation for the writing of a centennial narrative history of the program at the University of Connecticut.
History
Three acts signed by President Lincoln in 1862 shaped the U.S. Agricultural history: the act authorizing a U.S. Department of Agriculture; the Homestead Act, encouraging settlement of public domain lands; and the Morrill Act establishing land grant colleges in every state and placing instruction in agriculture and home economics in higher education.
The history and formation of the Cooperative Extension Service dates back to The Hatch Act of 1887 which established a cooperative bond between United States Department of Agriculture and the nation's land-grant colleges allocating annual federal funding for research. This was one of the ways to improve the productivity of the farms and by doing this, build up the economy and also help the communities. It was the driving force for the land-grant colleges to meet the agriculture's needs. The Smith-Lever Act in 1914 also helped to establish the Cooperative Extension Service by providing funds for cooperative administration of agricultural extension education by the United States Department of Agriculture and the state land grant colleges.
On April 21, 1881 the Connecticut General Assembly voted to establish the Storrs Agricultural School and in 1893, approved an act "establishing the Storrs Agricultural College [later the University of Connecticut] and providing for the distribution of money received from the United States for Educational purposes." With the passage of this act, the institution which would become the University of Connecticut was designated the state's land-grant college and the recipient of federal funds for agricultural education. One form of this agricultural education was the Cooperative Extension Service program.
The Cooperative Extension Service provides information to farmers and homemakers, and offers assistance in the production and marketing of farm products as well as home managment. The four main areas of Cooperative Extension Service involvement are agricultural production and farm management, homemaking and home economics, boys and girls clubs, and finally marketing and cooperation.
While the modern Cooperative Extension Service came into existence in 1914, the Connecticut Agricultural College, as the University of Connecticut was called at the time, offered educational outreach services as early as 1893. Professor A.B. Peebles provided the the initial push to start the program and in 1896 he initiated a two year plan of systematic reading for farmers. The Connecticut Agricultural College designated five-hundred dollars for the project and provided two traveling libraries for the students.
The Cooperative Extension Service took its modern form with the passage of the Smith-Lever Act of 1914, which charged land grant colleges, such as the Connecticut Agricultural College, to add the mission of outreach to their already existing functions. The Smith-Lever Act of 1914 sparked an active and energetic Cooperative Extension Service program at the University of Connecticut under which they formed 4-H Clubs and provided lectures in home economics.
World War I significantly increased the activities of the Cooperative Extension Service program. The program developed cooperative efforts with the State Food Division and the Federal Food Administration, and home demonstration activities were also increased as a result of the war.
After World War I, the Cooperative Extension Service again experienced a period of expansion. In 1919, the Connecticut General Assembly appropriation increased the program's budget from thirty thousand dollars to one-hundred thirty-four thousand dollars. In addition to increased funding, the Cooperative Extension Service also implimented agricultural specialists in areas such as rural health, clothing, and various disciplines of agricultural science.
In later years the Cooperative Extension Service developed an active cooperation with the U.S. Department of Agriculture as well as with other state agricultural agencies. By the late 1940s the Cooperative Extension Service was directing an increased attention toward groups such as the Parent-Teacher Association, Visiting Nurse Association, and other service clubs.
In 1989, the Cooperative Extension Service became the Cooperative Extension System. Today, the Cooperative Extension System at the University strives to help Connecticut's diverse population manage their family resources and develop strong family units through increased employability, bettering their decision making abilities, and by promoting enhanced self esteem. Through programs focused on the topics of parenting, 4-H and youth development, agriculture and the environment, nutrition and food safety, child care, money management, lead poisoning and health the CES serves to guide children, youth and adults in coping with the challenges of everyday living.
Scope and Content
The collection contains publications, reports, studies, documents and ephemeral materials collected and used used as background and research for the development and preparation for the writing of a centennial narrative history of the program at the University of Connecticut.
Arrangement
Inventory, ( undated, 1888- )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Dodd
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Organizations:
University of Connecticut.; Cooperative Extension Service (U.S.)
Family Names:
Places:
Storrs (Conn.)
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Artwork.; Scrap-Books.; Videocassettes.; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials in the collection have been transferred to the University Archives periodically since 1970.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: Inventory, undated, 1881-
  - CES History (Box 1)
    - Financial Records, 1987-1994
  - CES History (Box 2)
    - New London County, CT, 4-H, 1914-1956
  - CES History (Box 3)
    - USDA Publications, 2004-2006
    - CSREES Documents (USDA), circa 2005
    - General History, 1971-1992
    - Federal and Regional USDA, 1978-1979, 1998, 2004-2008
    - College Extension Publications - Not UConn, 2000-2006
    - UConn/ CES Reports and Publications, 1998-1993
  - CES History (Box 4)
    - 4-H Newsletters, University of Connecticut and State of CT, 1996-2007
    - National 4-H Council Documents, circa 2005
    - 4-H History, 1934-2002
      Includes two books and several photographs
  - CES History (Box 5)
    - Connecticut Home Economics Bulletin, 1944-1979
    - United Technologies, Double Dutch, Photographic Slides, 1980 February 29
    - "Making your tomorrow better", CES Home Economics, Photographic Slides, circa 1980
    - Unidentified Photographic Slides, circa 1981
    - Litchfield County, CT 4-H, Photographic Slides, 1977-1982
  - CES History (Box 6)
    - College of Agriculture Journals, 1994-1999
    - Drop in the Bucket Journal, 1995-1999
    - Farming Journals, 1999 January - February
    - Milestones, 1953-1979
    - Real Treeline Journals, 1997-1999
    - Agricultural Land Use and Preservation, Photographic Slides, cira 1981
      Includes cassette
    - "Enter Extension's World", Photographic Slides, circa 1978
    - Middlesex County, CT Photographic Slides, 1974-1981
  - CES History (Box 7)
    - Hartford County, CT, 4-H, 2007-2008
    - Litchfield County, CT, 4-H, 2003-2008
    - Middlesex County, CT, 4-H, 1996-2008
    - New London County, CT, 4-H, 1956-2008
    - Windham County, CT, 4-H, 1961, 2006-2007
    - Tolland County, CT, 4-H, 1936-1937, 2006-2007
    - Connecticut State 4-H, 1968-2007
    - Extension Publications - Not Connecticut, 1958-2004
    - Big E, 2002
    - Four Leaf Clover, 1929-1940
  - CES History (Box 8)
    - Water Quality NEMO, 1985-1993
    - Department of Extension, 1928-1953, 1982-1995
    - College Farm and Home Week, 1947
      Includes several photographs
    - Federal CES, Financial Records, 1985-1997
    - UConn, County, CT, Financial Records, 1951-1954
    - NASULGC and ECOP Meeting Minutes, 2000 February - 2002 February
    - CT/ CES, State Financial Records, 1945-1987
    - 4-H, CT Governor's Certificate of Recognition, 2006
  - CES History (Box 9)
    - College Documents, 1959-1998
    - CT Agriculture, 1929-2006
    - Connecticut Small Business Development Center Files, 1991-2006
    - NASULGC and ECOP Files, circa 2005
    - Extension Services History Files, circa 2005
      Includes computer programs, video cassette, books, and photographs
    - CES Documents, circa 1986
    - Agriculture and Extension Publications, 1942, 2006
    - National Books on Extension, 1965, 1989
  - CES History (Box 10)
    - Federal USDA Reports and Publications, 1989-1999
  - CES History (Box 11)
    - Farming and Farm Bureau Books and Pamphlets, 1891-1962
  - CES History (Box 12)
    - Federal USDA Reports and Publications, 1999-2007
    - USDA Publications, 1895-2000
  - CES History (Box 13)
    - Clean Scene Photographic Slides, 1978-1979
    - Marine AOV, Photographic Slides, 1978-1979
    - Multimedia Slides, 1975
    - Unidentified Photographs, undated, 1989-1990
  - CES History (Box 14)
    - University of Connecticut Nutmeg Yearbooks, 1881, 1916, 1925-1928, 1934, 1940, 1969
  - CT Home Economics Bulletins and Files, 1974-1990 (Box 15)
  - CES History (Box 16)
    - CT/ CES Annual and Congressional Reports, 1958-2006
  - CES History (Box 17)
    - Windham County, CT Files, 1917-1953, 1986-1996
  - CES History (Box 18)
    - Administration and Facilities Files, 1946-1996
    - Agricultural and Other Publications and Catalogues, 1986-2002
    - Unidentified Newspaper Clippings, 1971-1976
  - CES History (Box 19)
    - CT Food Policy, 1999, 2007
    - State Resources - Not UConn, 2006
    - CT Home Economics Programs, 1929-1988
    - CT/ CES Media and Newsletters, 1992-2003
      Includes CDs
    - CANR Leaders' Forum, 2007
    - UConn CANR Plant Sciences, 1949-1954, 1976-1980, 2006
      Includes photograph
    - National Resources - Not USDA or NASULGC, 1995-2006
      Includes videotape
    - Civil Rights Report, 1999
    - Unidentified Scrapbook - Topic: Milk, 1919-1956
  - CES History (Box 20)
    - Family Community Leadership Files, 1985-1991
  - CES History (Box 21)
    - USDA and State Soil and Production Agriculture Publications, 1941-1965
  - CES History (Box 22)
    - Impact Reports, 1997-2004
  - CES History (Box 23)
    - Impact Reports, 2005-2006
    - Annual Reports, 1980-1986
    - County Audits, 1946-1948
  - CES History (Box 24)
    - Annual Reports, 1923-1932
  - CES History (Box 25)
    - County Budgets, 1941-1951
    - CES Publications, 1986-2000
  - CES History (Box 26)
    - CES Publications, 1936-2004
  - CES History (Box 27)
    - Windham County, Farmers Association News, 1916-1943
  - CES History (Box 28)
    - USDA Publications, 1990-1999
    - Immigration Laws, 1986-1987
    - Extension Bulletins, 2004-2008
    - Extension Organization and Policy, 1915-1974
    - General Information, 1972-1991
    - CES Volunteer Files, 1998-2007
    - References: Milestones Articles, 2007
  - CES History (Box 29)
    - References, circa 1960-2007
  - CES History (Box 30)
    - Training Manuals, 1980-2000
  - CES History (Box 31)
    - Partner Organizations, 1961 - circa 2000
    - Commercial Publications, 1931, 1997-2003
    - Agricultural Experiment Station, 1931-2000
      Include 2 books
    - State of Connecticut Files, 1961-2000
    - General University Files, 1953-1994
  - CES History (Box 32)
    - 4-H Photographic Slides, 1975-1978
    - Using Connecticut's Land, Photographic Slides, 1977-1978
    - Agriculture, Photographic Slides, 1977-1981
    - Energy, Photographic Slides, 1977-1979
    - Home Economics, Photographic Slides, 1972-1981
    - Graphics and Media, Photographic Slides, 1977
    - CRO, Photographic Slides, 1977-1979 (Folder 20)
    - General, Photographic Slides, 1977-1978
    - Carigan, Photographic Slides, 1977
  - CES History (Box 33)
    - College of Agriculture Book, 1913
    - Unidentified Photograph, Undated
  - CES History (Box 34)
    - 4-H Photographs, 1920-2004
      Includes 2 cds and 3 video cassettes
    - Film and Slides, Undated
    - College of Agriculture, circa 1910
    - Agriculture and Farming Photos, 1932-1977
    - Home Economics Photos, circa 1980
    - Unidentified Photos, Undated
  - CES History (Box 35)
    - General CES Files and Photos, 1964-2007
    - Home Economics Photos, 1932-1974
    - Agriculture and Farming, 1918-1978
    - Unidentified Photographs, Undated
    - NASULGC Files, 1987-1998
    - College Reports, 2001
    - Volunteerism, 1998-2001
    - Dairy Committee Files, 1932-1936
    - UCANRAA Files, 1989-1995
    - NRAES Publications, 1995-2000
    - Farm Foundation Files, 1995-1997
    - E.P. Singsen Files, 1954-1977
  - CES History (Box 36)
    - College of Agriculture Files, 1963-2007
      Includes slides and 2 video cassettes
    - NRC Publications, 2002, 2004
    - Farm Bureau Documents, circa 1985
    - College Reports, 1920-1930
    - Litchfield County, CT Extension Housemakers, 1982-1993
    - Connecticut CES Long Range Plan, 1987
    - New England Documents, 1957-2005
  - Epsilon Sigma Phi Files (Box 37)
    - Membership Files, circa 1960-2000
    - National Files, 1978-2000
    - State Programs, 1988-1992
    - Foundation Files, 1994
    - National Constitution Bylaws, 1977-1983
    - State Newsletters, 1978-2007
    - Galaxy Conference, 1997
    - Joint Council Ext. Professional, 1993
    - Membership Fact Sheets, circa 1987-2002
    - Bylaws, 1964-2002
    - Extension Workers Creed, undated
      Includes 1 poster
    - ESP Records, 2001
    - Retirees Files, 1989-2002
    - Officers and Nominations, 1986-1993
    - ESP Reports, 1969-2000
  - Epsilon Sigma Phi Files (Box 38)
    - Agendas, 1979-2002
    - Minutes, 1968-2004
    - Managing Professional Challenges Conference, 1989
    - National Newsletters, 1984-1997
    - ESP Financials, 1966-2003
    - Questionaires and Surveys, 1971-2002
    - National Action, 1993
    - Photographs and CDs, 1982 - circa 2000
    - Awards and Scholarships, 1979-2002
  - Epsilon Sigma Phi Files (Box 39)
    - Chapter Member Notebook, 1999-2001
    - Chapter Member Handbook, 1999
      Includes 2 floppy disks